Finding aid to Hallie Flanagan Davis Papers CA.MS.00053
Smith College Archives
Hallie Flanagan Davis Papers
1911-1994
Smith College Archives
Flanagan, Hallie, 1890-1969.
CA.MS.00053
0.5 linear feet (1 document box)
Dean, Smith College, Professor of Drama, Head of the Federal Theater Project. Contains biographical material, correspondence, photographs, speeches, and writings.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Source unknown.
In 2018, letters to/from Hallie Flanagan Davis; biographical material; copy of play 'Heritage' related to Smith College were transferred from Hayner Library, Alton, IL. The material, which was a gift from Nancy Gent (a family friend), to Hayner Library in April 2018, was interfiled with exisiting papers.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into four series:
I. Biographical Materials
II. Correspondence
III. Photographs
IV. Writings
Biographical / Historical
Hallie Flanagan Davis was born on August 27, 1890 in Redfield, South Dakota. Her parents were Frederic Miller and Louise (Fisher) Ferguson. Davis got her Bachelor's degree at Grinnell College (Grinnell, Iowa) in 1911. In 1924, she earned her Master's degree from Radcliffe College. She had two short-lived marriages, both of which ended due to her husbands' deaths. The first, in 1912, was to John Murray Flanagan, who died in 1919. The second, in 1934, was to Phillip Haldane Davis, who died in 1940. Between the two marriages, Davis had two children and three step children.
In 1924-5, Hallie Flanagan Davis was an Associate Professor at Grinnell College, and the founder of their Experimental Theater. From 1925 until 1942, Davis worked as a Professor at Vassar College, where she also founded and directed their Experimental Theater. In 1935, she was asked to head the Federal Theater Project, which was part of the New Deal's W.P.A. She served as the head of the project until its end. In 1942, she accepted Smith College's offer to serve as Dean and a professor in the Drama Department. She resigned from her position as Dean in 1946 so that she could focus on the Drama Department, of which she was the chair, and on the Theater, of which she was the director. Davis retired from Smith in 1955. In 1962, the Studio Theater in Smith's new Center for the Performing Arts was named in her honor. She died on July 23, 1969.
Flanagan Davis' writings include: Arena, Shifting Scenes in the Modern European Theater, and Dynamo, the Story of the Vassar Theater. Her plays include: The Curtain, and E-mc2.
Scope and Contents
The Hallie Flanagan Davis papers contain biographical materials, correspondence, photographs, speeches and writings spanning Davis' career as a faculty member at Smith College.
Flanagan, Hallie, 1890-1969.; Smith College--Faculty.; Grinell College--Faculty.; Vassar College--Faculty.
- Series I: Biographical Materials
  Scope and Contents
  This section of the collection consists of awards and honors received by Davis and obituaries.
  - Biographical Materials (Awards and Honors), 1948 - 1964 (Box 743, Folder 1)
  - Biographical Materials, 1942 - 1994 (Box 743, Folder 2)
  - Biographical Materials (Obituaries), 1969 (Box 743, Folder 3)
- Series II: Correspondence
  This section of the collection contains one folder of personal correspondence dated from 1911 through 1948 and on folder of correspondence pertaining to the Theater Department at Smith College dated 1949.
  - Correspondence, 1911 - 1948 (Box 743, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence (Theater Dept), 1949 (Box 743, Folder 5)
- Series III: Photographs
  This section contains one folder of undated photographs.
  - Photographs, n. d. (Box 743, Folder 6)
- Series IV: Writings
  This section consists of eight speeches given by Davis ranging in date from 1939 through 1945 and three undated speeches, seven writings by Davis ranging in date from 1938 through 1955 including one undated writing and a copy of a thesis written by Ellen Senay Smith for her M. A. thesis from Tulane University.
  - Speech - "The Artist in the College", n. d. (Box 743, Folder 7)
  - Speech - Smith Assembly, 10 / 4 / 1945 (Box 743, Folder 8)
  - Speech - "The Contribution of the Arts to Democracy", n. d. (Box 743, Folder 9)
  - Speech - "Find your Weapon", 5 / 6 / 1944 (Box 743, Folder 10)
  - Speech - "For Tonight and For Tomorrow", 11 / 16 / 1942 (Box 743, Folder 11)
  - Speech - "In Which We Serve", 1 / 20 / 1943 (Box 743, Folder 12)
  - Speech - "Our Firm Estate", 6 / 16 / 1943 (Box 743, Folder 13)
  - Speech - "The Theater in a Changing, 12 / 5 / 1943 (Box 743, Folder 14)
  - Speech - "The Theater in the College", 5 / 11 / 1943 (Box 743, Folder 15)
  - Speech - "The Theater in the College", 1939 (Box 743, Folder 16)
  - Speech - "The Theater in the College", 4 / 28 / 1945 (Box 743, Folder 17)
  - Speech - "Women in the Theater", 3 / 11/ 1944 (Box 743, Folder 18)
  - Writings - The Postman Sometimes Rings Twice, 1946 (Box 743, Folder 19)
  - Teaching - Course Introduction ("Theater as a Life Force"), n. d. (Box 743, Folder 20)
  - Thesis - M. A. Thesis by Ellen Senay Smith, Tulane University, 1964 (Box 743, Folder 21)
  - Article - WPA, A Living Newspaper, 1938 (Box 743, Folder 22)
  - Writings - Can you Hear the Voices, n. d. (Box 743, Folder 23)
  - Writings - Covenant and Heritage, 1953; 1955 (Box 743, Folder 24)
  - Writings - E = MC 2, 1947; 1948 (Box 743, Folder 25)
  - Writings - Make with the Maximum, 1943 (Box 743, Folder 26)